Curriculum Vitae

KC Sivaramakrishnan

Computer Laboratory University of Cambridge sk826@cl.cam.ac.uk February 8, 2018

15 JJ Thomson Avenue Cambridge CB3 0FD Tel: +44 79828 42499

May 2011 - Dec 2014

Hyderabad, India

Summary

I am interested in the design and implementation of concurrent programming languages targeting scalable platforms such as many-core processors and compute clouds. My research spans programming models, compilers, static analysis, schedulers, threading systems, and memory management.

***** Education

PhD — Computer Science

Thosis Title: Experience Programming Abstractions for Weekly Consistent Systems	Purdue University, USA
Thesis Title: Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan	,
Master of Science — Computer Science	Aug 2008 – May 2011 Purdue University, USA
Bachelor of Engineering — Computer Science and Engineering	Aug 2004 – May 2008 PSG College of Technology Anna University, India
> Experience	
Senior Research Associate, University of Cambridge Advisors: Alan Mycroft, Anil Madhavapeddy	Nov 2017 – present Cambridge, UK
Research Fellow, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851	Oct 2015 – present
Research Fellow, Darwin College, Cambridge	Oct 2015 – present
Research Associate, University of Cambridge	Dec 2014 – Oct 2017
Research Assistant, Purdue University Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan	Aug 2008 – Dec 2014 West Lafayette, IN, USA
Teaching Assistant, Purdue University Undergraduate C Programming (CS180) Graduate Programming Languages (CS565)	West Lafayette, IN, USA Aug 2012 – Dec 2012 Aug 2011 – Dec 2011
Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge Advisors: Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, and Simon Peyton Jones	Feb 2012 – May 2012 Cambridge, UK
Research Intern, Samsung Information Systems America (R&D) Advisor: Daniel Waddington	May 2010 – Aug 2010 San Jose, CA, USA
Intern, Advanced Numerical Research and Analysis Group	Dec 2007 – Apr 2008

Grants, Awards and Recognitions

Advisor: Sankar Chnab

- Co-I, Feasibility of an Operating System for Interspatial Networking in a Built Environment, Centre for Digital Built Britain (CDBB), Mar 2018, £24,000.
- Research Fellowship, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851, 2015–2018, £102,000.
- Research Fellowship, Darwin College, Cambridge, 2015–2018, £900.

- Maurice H. Halstead Memorial Award for outstanding research in Software Engineering, Purdue University, 2014, \$4,000.
- Best paper award at Many-core Architecture Research Symposium at RWTH-Aachen, 2012, \$1,000.
- Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) Committer.
- SIGPLAN PAC travel grant for PLDI 2012 and POPL 2014, \$1,500 each.
- NSF travel grant for ICFP 2013, \$2,000.

Service

J6

J5

J2

- Organizer, Dagstuhl Seminar on "Algebraic Effect Handlers go Mainstream", Apr 2018.
- Program Committee member: PMLDC@ECOOP 2017, Off-the-beaten track (OBT) 2017, OCaml Workshop 2016, SPLASH-MARC symposium, 2013.
- Artifact Evaluation Committee member: ICFP 2018, PLDI 2015, PPoPP/CGO 2016.
- Reviewer: ECOOP, TODS, JFP, POPL, ICFP, ASPLOS, TLDI, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, Software: Practice and Experience.
- Organizer for Darwin College Science Seminar Series, Oct 2015 May 2017.

Journal Publications

Concurrent System Programming with Effect Handlers Stephen Dolan, Spiros Eliopolous, Daniel Hillerstrm, Anil Madhavapeddy, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Leo White Post-proceedings of the Symposium on Trends in Functional Programming (TFP) (accepted) Eff directly in OCaml Oleg, Kiselyov, KC Sivaramakrishnan Post-proceedings of the ML Workshop (accepted)

J4 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, Simon Peyton Jones Journal of Functional Programming (JFP)

Representation without Taxation: A Uniform, Low-Overhead, and High-Level Interface to Eventually Consistent Key-Value Stores

Mar 2016

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan *IEEE Data Engineering Bulletin*, 39(1): 52 – 64

Composable Scheduler Activations for Haskell

MultiMLton: A Multicore-aware Runtime for Standard ML

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan *Journal of Functional Programming (JFP)*, 24(6): 613 – 674

Efficient Sessions Feb 2013

J1 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Mohammad Qudeisat, Lukasz Ziarek, Karthik Nagaraj, Patrick Eugster Science of Computer Programming (SCP), 78(2): 147 – 167
Invited paper

Conference Publications

Continuation Passing Style for Effect Handlers

Sep 2017

Jun 2016

Nov 2014

C9 Daniel Hillerstrm, Sam Lindley, Robert Atkey, KC Sivaramakrishnan
International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD)

DaLi: Database as a Library

May 2017

Gowtham Kaki, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Thomas Gazagnaire, Anil Madhavapeddy, Suresh Jagannathan *The 2nd Summit on Advances in Programming Languages (SNAPL)*

Oral Presentation

C7	Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI)	Jun 2015		
C 6	Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Symposium on Practical Aspects of Declarative Languages (PADL)	Jan 2014		
C5	A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Many-core Architecture Research Community Symposium (MARC) Best paper award	Nov 2012		
C4	Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan International Symposium on Memory Management (ISMM)	Jun 2012		
C3	Composable Asynchronous Events Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI)	Jun 2011		
C2	Efficient Session Type Guided Distributed Interaction KC Sivaramakrishnan, Karthik Nagaraj, Lukasz Ziarek, Patrick Eugster International Conference on Coordination Models and Languages (COORDINATION)	June 2010		
C1	Partial Memoization of Concurrency and Communication Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP)	Sep 2009		
*	❖ Workshop Publications			
W13	A Memory Model for Multicore OCaml Stephen Dolan and KC Sivaramakrishnan OCaml Workshop	Sep 2017		
W12	Effectively Tackling the Awkward Squad Stephen Dolan, Spiros Eliopolous, Daniel Hillerstrm, Anil Madhavapeddy, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Leo White OCaml Workshop	Sep 2017		
W11	Mergeable Types Gowtham Kaki, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Samodya Abeysiriwardane, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop	Sep 2017		
W10	Concurrent System Programming with Effect Handlers Stephen Dolan, Spiros Eliopolous, Daniel Hillerstrm, Anil Madhavapeddy, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Leo White Symposium on Trends in Functional Programming (TFP)	Jun 2017		
W9	Eff directly in OCaml Oleg Kiselyov and KC Sivaramakrishnan JSSST Workshop on Programming and Programming Languages	Mar 2017		
W8	Lock-free programming for the masses KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tho Laurent OCaml Workshop	Sep 2016		
W7	Compiling Links Effect Handlers to the OCaml Backend Daniel Hillestrm, Sam Lindley, KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Worshop	Sep 2016		

W6	Eff Directly in OCaml Oleg Kiselyov and KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Workshop	Sep 2016
W5	Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects Stephen Dolan, Leo White, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Jeremy Yallop and Anil Madhavapeddy OCaml Workshop	Sep 2015
W4	Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop	Sep 2013
W3	Scalable Lightweight Task Management Schemes for MIMD Processors Daniel G. Waddington, Chen Tian, KC Sivaramakrishnan Workshop on Systems for Future Multi-Core Architectures (SFMA)	Apr 2011
W2	The Design Rationale for MultiMLton Suresh Jagannathan, Armand Navabi, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek ML Workshop	Sep 2010
W1	Lightweight Asynchrony using Parasitic Threads KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Raghavendra Prasad, Suresh Jagannathan Workshop on Declarative Aspects of Multicore Programming (DAMP)	Jan 2010
*	Technical Reports and Drafts	
T1	Featherweight Threads for Communication KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan	Nov 2011

Teaching/Advising

- Guest Lectures:
 - Arrows, Advanced Functional Programming, University of Cambridge, Lent '16.
 - Debugging, Programming in C and C++, University of Cambridge, Michelmas '15.
- Supervisions at University of Cambridge:
 - Databases, Lent '17, Michaelmas '17, Lent '16.
 - Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Lent '17, Michaelmas '17, Lent '16, Michaelmas '16, Lent '15.
 - Algorithms, Lent '15.
 - Object-oriented Programming, Michaelmas 2015–16.

Purdue University Computer Science Technical Report – TR-11-018

- Teaching assistantships at Purdue University
 - Undergraduate C Programming (CS180), Aug 2012 Dec 2012.
 - Graduate Programming Languages (CS565), Aug 2011 Dec 2011.
- Projects supervised:
 - Matevz Polijanc, University of Cambridge, A Reactive Programming model in OCaml, Oct 2017 Present.
 - Charlie Crisp, University of Cambridge, A Blockchain in Pure OCaml, Oct 2017 Present.
 - Henry Mercer, University of Cambridge, Systematic Concurrency Testing for Multicore OCaml, Oct 2017 Present.
 - Nicolas Assouad, ENS Paris, Hardware Support for Composable Lock-free Transactions, Mar 2017 Jun 2017.
 - Matt Harrison, University of Cambridge, Secure Decentralized Apps, Sep 2016 present.
 - Maxime Lesourd, ENS de Lyon, Verified CPS translation of handlers, Sep 2016 Mar 2017.

- Philip Dexter, Binghampton University, Approximate computing for OCaml, May 2016 Aug 2016.
- James Wright, University of Cambridge, Mechanized semantics of Algebraic Effects in OCaml, Sep 2015 Mar 2016.
- Armael Gueneau, ENS de Lyon, Algebraic Effects for js_of_ocaml, Sep 2015 Mar 2016.
- Theo Laurent, ENS, Reagents for Multicore OCaml, May 2015 Aug 2015.
- Guillain Potron, ENS de Lyon, Semantics of Irmin branch-consistent data store, March 2015 Aug 2015.

❖ Talks	
A deep dive into Multicore OCaml Garbage Collector System Research Group Seminar Comp	Jul 2017 outer Laboratory, University of Cambridge
Multicore OCaml GC JaneStreet Group	<i>Jun 2017</i> New York, NYC
Composable lock-free programming for Multicore OCaml ABCD Meeting	<i>Nov 2016</i> University of Edinburgh
Practical Algebraic Effect Handlers in Multicore OCaml LFCS Seminar	<i>Nov 2016</i> University of Edinburgh
Effective Concurrency and Parallelism in Multicore OCaml PL Seminar	Nov 2016 Indian Institute of Technology, Madras
Effective Concurrency and Parallelism in Multicore OCaml PL Seminar	Nov 2016 Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay
Effective parallelism with Reagents Facebook Faculty Summit	Sep 2016 London, UK
Multicore OCaml and Programming with Reagents LDN Functionals	Aug 2016 Jane Street UK, London
Effect handlers in Multicore OCaml Dagstuhl Seminar	<i>Mar 2016</i> Dagstuhl, Germany
Arrows and Reagents Invited Lecture, Advanced Functional Programming	<i>Mar 2016</i> Cambridge, UK
Concurrent and Multicore OCaml: A deep dive Facebook Tech Talk	<i>Jan 2016</i> Menlo Park, CA
OCaml Platform: Update OCaml Consortium Meeting	<i>Nov 2015</i> Paris, France
Multicore OCaml: Update OCaml Developer's Meeting	<i>Nov 2015</i> Paris, France
Silence is Golden: Controlling Communication and Coordination in Distributed Darwin College Science Seminar	Databases Oct 2015 Cambridge, UK
Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects OCaml Workshop 2015	Sep 2015 Vancouver, Canada
Quelea: Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores Computer Laboratory, University of Cambridge	<i>Apr 2015</i> Cambridge, UK
Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems	Dec 2014

Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony PADL 2014

Functional Abstractions for Practical and Scalable Concurrent Programming

PhD Defense

Invited Lecture

Jan 2014 San Diego, CA

Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK

Purdue University

Mar 2014

Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud

ML Workshop 2013

Sep 2013 Boston, MA

A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC

MARC 2012

Nov 2012 RWTH Aachen

Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness

ISMM 2012, Beijing

Wrestling Wednesdays, Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Jun 2012 May 2012

Lightweight Concurrency in GHC

Wrestling Wednesdays

May 2012

Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Efficient Session Type guided Distributed Interaction

COORDINATION 2012

Jun 2012 CWI Amsterdam

References

Suresh Jagannathan

Professor
Department of Computer Science
Purdue University
305 N University St
West Lafayette, IN 47906, USA
suresh@cs.purdue.edu

Jan Vitek

Professor of Computer Science College of Computer & Information Science Northeastern University 440 Huntinton Av Boston, MA 02115, USA j.vitek@neu.edu

Anil Madhavapeddy

University Lecturer Computer Laboratory University of Cambridge 15 JJ Thomson Av Cambridge, CB3 0FD, UK anil.madhavapeddy@cl.cam.ac.uk

Simon Peyton Jones

Principal Researcher
Programming Principles and Tools
Microsoft Research Ltd
21 Station Rd
Cambridge CB1 2FB, UK
simonpj@microsoft.com